American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5001 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm
1905- 1945
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Association for Labor Legislation
5001 mf
7.89 cubic feet
71 microfilm reels
Microfilm, broadsides (notices).
Records consist of correspondence, committee minutes, reports, financial records and research documents generated by staff members to facilitate legislative programs. These research materials deal with the following subjects: general labor law, general social insurance, health insurance, occupational safety, diseases and accidents, labor law administration, pensions and old age benefits, unemployment, wages, hours of work, working conditions, workers' compensation and unionism.
3336856
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 19, 2016
Biographical / Historical
The American Association for Labor Legislation was formed to promote uniformity of labor legislation and to encourage the study of labor conditions with a view toward promoting desirable legislation.
The Association was founded as a branch of the International Association for Labor Legislation. Preliminary discussions about forming the group occurred during 1905 and culminated in the first meeting of the Association held on February 15, 1906, in New York City.
During the Association's first few years, three basic objectives were established: to serve as the American branch of the International Association for Labor Legislation; to promote uniformity of labor legislation in the United States; and to encourage the study of labor conditions with a view toward promoting desirable labor legislation.
John Bertram Andrews was appointed executive secretary in 1909. His wife, Irene Osgood Andrews, eventually became associate secretary. John Andrews, as lobbyist, lecturer, author and editor of the publication THE AMERICAN LABOR LEGISLATION REVIEW, became the motivating force of the Association. Broadly speaking, the American Association for Labor Legislation set the following goals: the alleviation of adverse working conditions; the creation of laws to protect safety and health on the job; and the provision of compensation in times of unemployment and benefits for workers no longer able to participate in the labor force. To facilitate the implementation of the Association's interests, study groups were established to investigate labor conditions. Active lobbying was undertaken in support of protective labor legislation in state and federal legislatures, and critiques were published concerning pending bills. The lifetime of the Association roughly corresponded to Andrew's lifetime; its activities ceased after his death in 1943.
Scope and Contents
Records consist of correspondence, committee minutes, reports, financial records and research documents generated by staff members to facilitate legislative programs. These research materials deal with the following subjects: general labor law, general social insurance, health insurance, occupational safety, diseases and accidents, labor law administration, pensions and old age benefits, unemployment, wages, hours of work, working conditions, workers' compensation and unionism.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5001: American Association for Labor Legislation Records 5001 PAM: American Association for Labor Legislation Pamphlet File 5002: American Association for Social Security Records
Depressions -- 1929 -- United States; Hours of labor -- United States; Industrial accidents -- United States; Industrial safety -- United States; Health insurance -- United States; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Occupational diseases -- United States; Pensions -- United States; Social security -- United States; Unemployment -- United States; Lobbyists.; Alien labor. Insurance. United States.; Anthrax. Occupational diseases.; Children. Employment. Law and legislation. United States.; Children. Law and legislation. United States.; Coal mining industry. Safety regulations. United States.; Compressed air industry. United States. State supervision.; Employment agencies. United States. State supervision.; Hours of labor. Law and Legislation. United States.; Industrial hygiene. Law and legislation. United States.; Industrial relations. United States. State supervision.; Industrial safety. Law and legislation. United States.; Industrial safety. Law and legislation. United States.; Insurance, Disability. Law and legislation. United States.; Insurance, Health. Law and legislation. Germany.; Insurance, Health. Law and legislation. Great Britain.; Insurance, Health. Law and legislation. United States.; Insurance, Life. Health facilities. United States.; Insurance, Unemployment. Law and legislation. United States.; Interstate commerce. Law and legislation. United States.; Iron industry. United States. Taxation.; Kern Bill; Labor and laboring classes. United States. Medical examinations.; Laboratory technicians. Licenses. United States.; Lead industry workers. United States. Diseases and hygiene.; Lead poisoning. Occupational diseases.; Lungs. Dust diseases. Prevention.; Management. Employee participation. United States.; Match industry workers. United States. Diseases and hygiene.; Migrant labor. United States. Insurance.; Mine inspection. Law and legislation. United States.; Mine inspection. United States. State supervision.; Mine safety. Law and legislation. United States.; National health insurance. United States.; Old age assistance. United States. State supervision.; Pensions. Agriculture. United States.; Pensions. Law and legislation. United States.; Phosphorous poisoning. Occupational diseases.; Public welfare. California. State supervision.; Public welfare. New York (State). State supervision.; Public welfare. Pennsylvania. State supervision.; Public welfare. United States.; Radium poisoning. Occupational diseases.; Silicosis. Occupational diseases.; Social legislation. United States. Bibliographies.; Social security. Law and legislation. United States.; Steel industry. United States. Taxation.; Strikes and lockouts. Law and legislation. United States.; Trade-union label. United States.; Unemployment. Law and legislation. United States.; Unemployment relief. Law and legislation. United States.; Unemployment relief. New York (State).; Unemployment relief. Wisconsin.; Vocational rehabilitation. Law and legislation. United States.; Wages. Law and legislation. United States.; Wages. Minimum wage. Law and legislation. United States.; Wages. Minimum wage. United States.; Wages. Women. Law and legislation. United States.; Walsh-Healy Bill.; Women. Employment. Law and legislation. United States.; Women. Law and legislation. United States.; Workers' compensation. Civil service. United States.; Workers' compensation. Law and legislation. United States.; Workers' compensation. Merchant marine. United States.; Workers' compensation. Railroads. United States.; Workers' compensation. Stevedores. United States.; Workers' compensation. United States.; Working conditions. Law and legislation. United States.; Working conditions. United States.; United States. Economic policy. To 1933.; United States. Economic policy. 1933-1945.; United States. Emigration and immigration.; United States. Public works.; Amalgamated Association of Street and Electric Railway Employees of America; Amalgamated Association of Street, Electric Railway and Motor Coach Employees of America; American Association for Labor Legislation; American Association for Old Age Security; American Association for Social Security; American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Association for the Advancement of Science. Committee of One Hundred on National Health.; American Economic Association; American Federation of Labor; American Federation of Teachers; American Medical Association; American Mining Congress; British Medical Association; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America.; Hull-House (Chicago, Ill.); Illinois State Federation of Labor; Industrial Commission of Wisconsin; International Association for Labor Legislation; International Labour Office; International Longshoremen's Association; International Seamen's Union of America; International Typographical Union; Louisiana. Board of Health.; Massachusetts. Bureau of Statistics.; Massachusetts. Commission on Old Age Pensions.; Massachusetts. State Board of Health.; Mining Safety Coordinating Committee; Mining Standardization Coordinating Committee; National Association of Manufacturers (U.S.); National Child Labor Committee (U.S.); National Civic Federation; National Consumers' League; National Employment Exchange (New York, N.Y.); National Metal Trades Association (U.S.); National Woman's Party; New York Conference for Unemployment Reserves Legislation; New York (State). Department of Health.; New York (State). Department of Labor; New York (State). Factory Investigating Commission.; New York (State). Industrial Commission.; North American Civic League for Immigrants; Ohio State Federation of Labor; Prudential Insurance Company of America; Railway Labor Executives Association; Russell Sage Foundation; Saint Lawrence Seaway Development Corporation; Teachers Guild Associates; United States. Bureau of Animal Industry.; United States. Bureau of Labor.; United States. Bureau of Labor Statistics.; United States. Bureau of Liability Insurance.; United States. Bureau of Mines.; United States. Commission on Economic Security.; United States. Commission on Industrial Relations.; United States. Commission on Labor Statistics.; United States. Department of Commerce.; United States. Department of Commerce and Labor.; United States. Department of Labor.; Wisconsin. Commission for Unemployment Reserves Legislation.; Women's Educational and Industrial Union (Boston, Mass.); Abbot, Grace. 1878-1936.; Addams, Jane. 1860-1935.; Adler, Felix. 1851-1933.; Alexander, Magnus W. (Magnus Washington), 1870-1932.; Allen, James E., 1911-; Almy, Frederic, 1858- 1935.; Altmeyer, Arthur J. (Arthur Joseph), 1891-1972.; Anderson, Mary, 1872-1964.; Andrews, John B. (John Bertram), 1880-1943; Arnstein, Leo; Bain, Harry Foster, 1872-1948; Bakke, E. Wight. (Edward Wight), 1903-1971; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884- 1981; Barnes, Charles B. (Charles Brinton), 1870-; Bauer, Stephen.; Beaman, Middleton.; Beck, James D.; Boudin, Leonard, 1912-1989; Boyle, James, 1853-1939; Brake, Edwin V.; Raushenbush, Elizabeth Brandeis; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz,1856-1941; Brandt, Lilian, 1873-; Breckinridge, Sophonisba Preston, 1866-1948.; Brown, Gerald W., (Gerald Wayne), 1939-; Brue`re, Robert W. (Robert Walter), 1876-1964; Burke, James T.; Cammer, Harold; Carlton, Frank T.; Cease, D. L.; Chadbourn, Thomas L. (Thomas Lincoln), 1871-; Chamberlain, Joseph P. (Joseph Perkins), 1873- 1951.; Cheney, Howell, 1870-1957; Chlopek, Anthony; Chubb, Irene Sylvester; Clauson, Andrew; Clively, C.; Colby, Everett, 1897-1943.; Coman, Katharine, 1857-1915.; Commons, John R. (John Rogers), 1862-1945; Coulter, John L.; Count, George; Coyle, Grace Longwell, 1892-; Davies, Edgar T. (Edgar Thomas), 1873-; Dawson, Miles Menander, 1863-1942; De Leon, Solon, 1883-; Devine, Edward T. (Edward Thomas), 1867-1948; Dewey, Davis Rich, 1858-1942.; Doak, William Nuckles, 1882-1933; Dodd, Bella V., 1904-1969; Dodd, Walter F.; Doten, Carroll (Carroll Warren), 1871-1942; Douglas, Dorothy J.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Draper, Ernest Gallaudet, 1885-1954; Dreier, Mary E. (Mary Elisabeth), 1875-1963; Drown, Frank S.; Dummer, Mrs. W. F.; Eastman, Crystal, 1881-1928; Eaves, Lucile, 1869-; Eells, Howard P., 1855-1919; Ellinwood, Everett E., 1862-1943; Ely, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1854-1943; Epstein, Abraham, 1892-1942; Erskine, Lillian; Esch, John J. (John Jacob), 1861-1941; Evans, Elizabeth Glendower; Faichild, Milton, 1865-1939; Farnam, Henry W. (Henry Walcott), 1853-1933; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003; Favill, Henry B.; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Fitch, John A. (John Andrews), 1881-1959; Fitzgerald, Roy G. (Roy Gerald), 1875-1962; Fletcher, Richard H.; Ford, Lucia O.; Frankel, Lee K. (Lee Kaufer), 1867-1931; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Franklin, S. M.; Freund, Ernst, 1864-1932; Frey, John P. (John Philip), 1871-1957; Furuseth, Andrew, 1854-1938; Fuss, Henri; Fuster, Edward; Gellhorn, Walter, 1906- 1995; Gettemy, Charles F. (Charles Ferris), 1868-; Gilbreth, Frank B. (Frank Bunker), 1868-1924; Gilmore, C. Edwin; Glenn, John M.; Glicksman, Nathan; Golden, John; Goldmark, Josephine, 1877-1950; Goldwater, S.S. (Sigismund Schulz), 1873-1942; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Gordon, Merritt J. b. 1857; Grant, Luke; Gray, John H. (John Henry), 1859-1946; Gray, R.S.; Green, William, 1872-1952; Hall, Fred S. (Fred Smith),1870-1946; Halsey, Olga; Hamilton, Alice, 1869-1970; Hammond, M. B. (Matthew Brown), 1868-1933; Handley, J. J.; Hanger, G. W. W. (Glossbrenner Wallace William), 1866-1935; Hard, William, 1878-1962; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Harper, C. A.; Harrington, Charles, 1865-1943; Harrington, D.; Hatch, L. W. (Leonard Williams), 1869-1958; Haynes, John Randolph; Haythorn, Samuel R.; Henderson, C. R.; Hendly, Charles; Hering, Frank (Frank Earl), 1874-1943; Higday, Hamilton; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946; Hoffman, Frederick L. (Frederick Ludwig), 1865-1946; Hohaus, Reinhard; Holbrook, Elmer Allen, 1881-1957; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Ingram, Frances; James, Margaret; Jansen, William; Jenks, J. W.; Johnson, Ethel M.; Judson, Frederick N. (Frederick Newton), 1845-1919; Kasten, Marie; Keating, Edward, 1875-1965; Kellogg, Arthur; Kellogg, Paul Underwood, 1879-1958; Kelley, Florence, 1859-1932; Kennedy, Thomas; Kingsbury, Susan M. (Susan Myra), 1870-1949; Kirk, William; Kratz, John Aubel,1884-; La Follette, Robert M. (Robert Marion), 1895-1953; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Lambert, Alexander, 1861-1939; Lapp, John A. (John Augustus), 1880-; Lathrop, Julia C.; Launer, William; Lazard, Max, 1875-; Leaderman, Abraham; Lee F.; Leeds, William M.; Lefkowitz, Abraham, 1884-1956; Lescohier, Don D. (Don Divance), 1883-1961; Lindsay, Samuel McCune, 1869-1960; Linville, Henry (Henry Richardson), 1866-1941; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974; London, Meyer, 1871-1926; Lorenz, Max, 1901-1975; Lovejoy, Owen R. (Owen Reed), 1866-1961; Low, Seth, 1850-1916; Lubin, Isador, 1896-1978; Lynch, James; Macy, V. E. (V. Everett); Magnusson, Leifur, 1882-; Mahon, W. A.; Mallery, Otto Tod, 1881-1956; Marburg, Theodore, 1862-1946; Marot, Helen, 1865-1940; Martin, John; Martindale, Frederick C.; McCall, Sidney; McCrea, Roswell C. (Roswell Cheney), 1876-1951; McDowell, Mary Elizabeth Smith, 1870-1897; McEwen, W. E.; McKelway, Alexander Jeffrey, 1866-1918; McKitrick, Reuben; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Meeker, Royal, 1873-1953; Mercer, H. V. (Hugh Victor); Meserole, Darwin J.; Metcalf, Henry C. (Henry Clayton), 1867-1942; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005; Milner, Lucille, 1888-; Mitchell, Wesley C. (Wesley Clair), 1874-1948; Morgan, Anne; Morrison, Frank, 1859-1949; Moseley, Ned, 1846-1911; Moskowkitz, Henry L.; Munsterberg, Hugo, 1863-1916; Neill, Charles P. (Charles Patrick), 1865-1942; Nestor, Agnes, 1880-1948; Neustadt, Richard M.; Norris,
3336856
- Correspondence: 1905, Oct 12 - 1909, Mar 20., 1905-1909 (Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This early correspondence relates almost entirely to the formation and early administration of the American Association for Labor Legisla-tion (AALL). Much of the initiative for its inauguration was taken by Adna F. Weber and Henry W. Farnam, whose interest in the International Association for Labor Legislation (IALL) inspired the establishment of its American counterpart. A circular and an invitation to attend the general meeting to organize the American section of the IALL on Feb. 15, 1906, drew favorable response from several persons who would later be influential in the Association, notably Samuel Gompers and Miles Mehander Dawson. The formal founding of the AALL dates from that 1906 meeting, and subsequent correspondence deals with the leadership and personnel problems of the infant association, as well as with the relationship of the new organization to the IALL. Richard T. Ely, first president of the AALL, wrote to Weber (2/26/07) commenting that the AALL needed a paid representative to give his full time to the work. The perennial problem of fund raising became a theme early in the organization's correspondence. During 1908, the course that the AALL was to follow for the next few years was developed. John R. Commons, then secretary, wrote to Dr. Henry B. Favill of the American Medical Association expressing a desire to meet with him and Dr. Alice Hamilton to discuss the investigation of occupational health and disease (1/21/08). This dialogue accelerated the development of a standard nomenclature for occupational disease and a proposal to investigate and recommend standards for industrial hygiene. Newly appointed Assistant Secretary Irene Osgood exchanged letters with Margaret D. Robins. Their correspondence concerned the Association's desire to investigate industrial diseases and poisons, and the plans for establishment of state chapters. Support for the organization was sought and won from socially conscious national leaders, including Louis Brandeis, Edward T. Devine, Samuel Gompers, and Alice Hamilton. The assistance of reform-minded groups such as the National Child Labor Committee was also successfully solicited. Early in 1909, Commons and Osgood suggested to Henry W. Farnam that John Andrews would make an excellent executive secretary. There was some question at this juncture as to whether the official stationery of the Association should carry the union label. Arguments on this issue went on for several years and are symptomatic of the organization's ambivalent attitude toward organized labor. Dr. Alice Hamilton continued her work with the AALL on industrial poisons and her letter to Osgood (2/13/09) suggested that a study of the match industry be undertaken because of its widespread use of poisonous white phosphorous.
- Correspondence: 1909, Mar 22 - 1910, Mar 18., 1909-1910 (Reel 2)
  The investigation into phosphorous poisoning continued and developed into the "Phossy Jaw" study. Interest arose in the Association in workmen's compensation and the Illinois 10-Hour Law, and John Andrews became the paid executive of the organization at about this time. Louis Brandeis wrote to Arthur Kellogg (5/26/09) about the pension bill of the Boston and Maine Railroad. The letter is significant for its early discussion of certain provisions which eventually were adopted into the American old age pension system. Correspondence during this period relates: to changes in legislation in regard to job hazards, insurance, employment office regulations, and child labor. The organization cooperated extensively with Brandeis and Josephine Goldmark in the preparation of material with which to fight defeat of the Illinois 10-Hour Law. Louis Brandeis expressed his gratitude to Andrews (11/30/09) for the information Andrews gathered for Brandeis' work on the 10-Hour case brief. John R. Commons wrote Henry W. Farnam (12/25/09), suggesting that the Association would do better to concern itself with active lobbying for measures it supported rather than with organizing. Since the state branches of the Association were not proving satisfactory. Commons thought that they should be discontinued. Early in 1910 the executive office was transferred to New York City where it remained for the life of the Association. In February John Andrews began to collect information on a contributory workmen's compensation insurance plan; and the Association continued to refine this plan for the next thirty years.
- Correspondence: 1910, Mar 19 - July 25. (Reel 3)
  The development of campaigns for workmen's compensation and against the use of poison phosphorous continued. A campaign to obtain workmen's compensation in New York State had begun in March. Miles Dawson wrote to Andrews (5/17/10) explaining how the use of poison phosphorous could be prohibited by means of federal legislation.
- Correspondence: 1910, July 26 - 1911, Feb 28., 1910-1911 (Reel 4)
  During this period, the Association worked intensively on its first piece of federal legislation, the bill to ban the use of white phosphorous in the manufacture of matches.
- Correspondence: 1911, March 1 - 1911, August 31. (Reel 5)
  During this period, the Association worked intensively on its first piece of federal legislation, the bill to ban the use of white phosphorous in the manufacture of matches. In August, 1916, Henry W. Farnam wrote to Stephen Bauer of the IALL (8/9/11) announcing that John Andrews and Irene Osgood had been married on the previous day. During the fall, preparations for the annual meeting were made and John Andrews wrote Ernst Freund (11/1/10) about the programs that would be emphasized in 1911. Phosphorous prohibition topped the list, followed by investigations of industrial disease, reporting of industrial accidents, workmen's compensation, factory inspection and, in cooperation with the National Child Labor Committee, Consumer's League and Women's Trade Union League, child labor and hours of labor for women. Congressman John Each, sponsor of the match bill, wrote often in regard to various provisions and problems of the bill. At the end of January a resolution was passed, authorizing the publication of the American Labor Legislation Review, with John Andrews as editor, a position that he held until his death. The Review was published quarterly and much of the correspondence over the years concerns authors and articles for this publication.
- Correspondence: 1911, Sept 1 - 1912, Feb 18., 1911-1912 (Reel 6)
- Correspondence: 1912, Feb 19 - Aug 31. (Reel 7)
  Vigorous publicity and lobbying efforts culminated in the passage of the bill prohibiting poison phosphorous in matches. The bill, sponsored by Congressmen Hughes and Each, was signed into law in April. The following month a more general study of industrial poisons and the diseases they caused was begun.
- Correspondence: 1912, Sept 1 - 1913, Feb 6., 1912-1913 (Reel 8)
  John Andrews exhibited interest in conducting a minimum wage investi-gation in New York State and continued to push for workmen's compensation there, insisting on a compulsory system. The problem of lead poisoning in industry also received much attention during this period. Henry Seager and Seth Low corresponded on the questions of mediation and compulsory arbitration. Samuel Gompers, incensed at the position that John Andrews and other "...progressive social worker types" had taken against the representatives appointed by President Taft to the Industrial Relations Commission, criticized Andrews and the AALL in the American Federationist and elsewhere. Andrews' lengthy reply (1/23/13) called upon Gompers to apologize publicly for calling him stupid and arrogant.
- Correspondence: 1913, Feb 7 - Aug 31. (Reel 9)